Guide to the Roy E. Huffman Papers1923-1990
Montana State University Library, Archives and Special Collections, Manuscript Collections
Roy E. Huffman Papers
1923-1990
Montana State University Library, Archives and Special Collections, Manuscript Collections
2349
11.60 linear feet 29 boxes
The Roy E. Huffman Papers consist of materials are mostly typewritten with some handwritten notes and letters, and include photocopies or reprints of previously published materials, reports, speeches and presentations; plans, programs, schedules, studies, and numerous papers related to his professional positions at MSU; numerous research notes and unfinished manuscript pages with bibliographical materials and citations; personal and professional correspondence; and clippings from newspapers and journals. Subjects are wide ranging but can be characterized into several categories: a) files on topics of general interest or research interest; b) files related to specific organizations, conferences, symposia or programs both professional and governmental (these may have correspondence and attachments included); c) files related to the research and publication of Roy Huffman's writings; d) files related to Montana State University (Montana State College before 1962) which may be by subject; by department; by specific positions Huffman held during his career; by committee, program, institutional or branch names; by faculty, students or individuals; or as miscellaneous items. e) correspondence: alphabetical files of a professional or personal nature maintained by Huffman plus individually named correspondence files of colleagues intimately involved with his research and writing as well as politicians and selected projects or organizations.
Professional and personal papers created or collected by Roy E. Huffman were donated to Montana State University on August 19, 1996 by his wife Menga Huffman. Any papers related to Huffman's work on the Montana Board of Natural Resources and Conservation were removed and integrated into Collection 2094, Montana Board of Natural Resources and Conservation Records, 1976-1981.
Roy E. Huffman was born April 12, 1916 and raised on a wheat farm in Chouteau County, Montana. He attended rural schools and graduated from Highwood High School in 1932. He married Menga Herzog in 1939 and had three children. He received his B.S. in Agricultural Economics from Montana State College in 1938, his M.S. in Agricultural Economics from the University of Maryland in 1939 and his PhD in Agricultural Economics from the University of Wisconsin in 1952. He began his career as an Agricultural Economist for the U.S. Department of Agriculture during 1939-1942. In 1942 he started his work at Montana State College as an Instructor in Agricultural Economics. After serving in the U.S. Navy in World War II from 1943-1946 he returned to Montana State College as an Assistant Professor of Agricultural Economics and Economics,1946-1950; Associate Professor from 1950-1953; and from 1953 to 1958 he was Professor and Head of the Department of Agricultural Economic and Rural Sociology: Economics and Sociology. In 1958 he became the Dean of Agriculture and Director of the Agricultural Experiment Station. In 1965 he was appointed as the first Vice President for Research. He served in that capacity until his retirement in 1976. Concurrent with the Vice Presidency he was Executive Director, Endowment and Research Foundation (1965-1976); Director, Montana University Joint Water Resources Research Center (1965-1969, 1973-1974); and Acting Dean of Graduate Studies (1975-1976). Roy Huffman was a prolific writer with over 100 titles to his credit including the book Irrigation Development and Public Water Policy (Ronald Press, 1953) and research bulletins, journal papers, magazine articles, conference papers and monographs. He promoted the modernization of agriculture through wise land use, water conservation, irrigation and farm management techniques. He was a member of the American Agricultural Economics Assn., Western Agricultural Economics Assn., Agricultural History Society, American Association of University Professors, Soil Conservation Society of America, and several honor societies. Among many awards, he received the Montana State University Blue and Gold Award for Distinguished Service in 1975. Outside the university he has served as a consultant to federal, state and private agencies, notably the Missouri River Basin Planning and Columbia Basin Consulting Boards of the U.S. Dept. of Interior; he was a member of numerous governmental and professional councils and committees including the National Association of State Universities and Land Grant Colleges; and participated as a speaker or presenter of papers at many conferences and proceedings in both academic and commercial arenas. After his retirement in 1976, he was appointed a member of the Montana Board of Natural Resources and Conservation by Governor Thomas L. Judge and served from 1977-1981. An active member of the greater community, he promoted tours of Russia and China for People to People, was active with the Museum of the Rockies and local civic projects. Dr. Roy E. Huffman died at age 78 on November 10, 1994.
Roy Huffman's collected and created papers were organized by him in alphabetical files by subject. Except for a few duplicated files, the papers are arranged as Roy Huffman kept them with loose papers and untitled files placed within the alphabetic sequence. The materials are mostly typewritten with some handwritten notes and letters, and include photocopies or reprints of previously published materials, reports, speeches and presentations; plans, programs, schedules, studies, and numerous papers related to his professional positions at MSU; numerous research notes and unfinished manuscript pages with bibliographical materials and citations; personal and professional correspondence; and clippings from newspapers and journals. Subjects are wide ranging but can be characterized into several categories: a) files on topics of general interest or research interest; b) files related to specific organizations, conferences, symposia or programs both professional and governmental (these may have correspondence and attachments included); c) files related to the research and publication of Roy Huffman's writings; d) files related to Montana State University (Montana State College before 1962) which may be by subject; by department; by specific positions Huffman held during his career; by committee, program, institutional or branch names; by faculty, students or individuals; or as miscellaneous items. e) correspondence: alphabetical files of a professional or personal nature maintained by Huffman plus individually named correspondence files of colleagues intimately involved with his research and writing as well as politicians and selected projects or organizations. Representation of government agencies including the Federal Farm Security Administration, U.S. Department of Agriculture, Energy Research and Development Administration, National Science Foundation, and regional entities such as the Missouri River Basin Commission and Columbia River Basin Inter-Agency Committee, Great Plains Agricultural Council, Montana Experiment Stations and Extension Service, and the Water Resources Research Center. Publications and publishers include Big Sky Books of the Endowment and Research Foundation of MSU, the Ronald Press and various journal publications. Representative files for professional and academic interests include the National Association of State Universities and Land Grant Colleges, American Agricultural Economics Assn., Western Agricultural Economics Assn., Agricultural History Society, American Association of University Professors, Soil Conservation Society of America, Sigma Xi and others. China (People to People), Russia, Saudi Arabia (agricultural projects), and other countries have individual files. Several untitled files containing research notes, citations and a large rough draft manuscript were combined with research note files with the name Omnibus.
In 1970, both Merrill G. Burlingame and Elmer Starch wrote Roy Huffman about a proposed manuscript Huffman had been working on. The work began in the mid-60s as a book on Fairway Farms and the influence of that program. Margarita "Rita" McDonald assisted with the research and rough draft materials. It apparently evolved into a larger project to produce a book about the influence on farming by the Montana State College Agriculture Department and the Montana experience which resulted in changes in land use, farm techniques, irrigation, family farms and government assistance across the nation. Individuals of note present in files are Governor Tim Babcock, Hugo G. Eck, Nicholas Helburn, Governor Thomas L. Judge, Maurice M. Kelso, Carl F. Kraenzel, Senator Mike Mansfield, Margarita "Rita" McDonald; MSU Presidents: Leon Johnson, Carl W. McIntosh, Roland R. Renne, William J. Tietz, Jr.; Mont H. Saunderson, Elmer A. Starch, Carl F. Taeusch and M. L. Wilson. Roy Huffman's diverse interests are also reflected in files for the Museum of the Rockies, conservation and reclamation issues, arts and humanities, political and legislative issues, energy and water policies, and some personal memento and joke files.
This collection is open for research without restrictions.
Agricultural History Society; American Agricultural Economics Association; American Association of University Professors; Columbia River Basin Inter-Agency Committee; Great Plains Agricultural Council; Missouri River Basin Commission; Montana Agricultural Experiment Station; Montana Extension Service in Agriculture and Home Economics; Montana State College. Faculty; Montana State University--Bozeman-Administration; Montana University Joint Water Resources Research Center; National Association of State Universities and Land-Grant Colleges; National Science Foundation (U.S.); Society of the Sigma Xi; Soil Conservation Society of America; United States-Dept. of Agriculture; United States-Energy Research and Development Administration; United States-Farm Security Administration; Western Agricultural Economics Association
Agricultural economists--Montana--Bozeman; Agricultural consultants; Agricultural innovations--Montana; Agricultural innovations--United States; Agriculture and state-Montana; Agriculture and state-United States; Agriculture--China; Agriculture-Economic aspects-Study and teaching-Montana-Bozeman; Agriculture-Saudi Arabia; Agriculture-Soviet Union; College administrators-Montana-Bozeman; College teachers--Montana--Bozeman
- Agricultural change: news clippings and articles (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Agricultural Economics course: Economic development and environmental values (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Agricultural Economics course: Economics of irrigated agriculture (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Agricultural Economics course: Economics of irrigated agriculture - Billings class (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Agricultural Economics course: Farm and ranch management (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Agricultural Economics course: Rural society (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Agricultural Economics Department correspondence: 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Agricultural Economics Department correspondence: 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Agricultural Economics Department correspondence: 1946-1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Agricultural History Society (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Agricultural Marketing Service (Box 1, Folder 11)
- "Agriculture in the Great Plains, 1876-1930" (Symposium), 1976 June (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Alpha Gamma Rho (Box 1, Folder 13)
- American Agricultural Economics Association (AAEA) (Box 1, Folder 14)
- American Association of University Professors (AAUP) (Box 1, Folder 15)
- American Association of University Professors - Committee on Salaries and Promotions (Box 1, Folder 16)
- American Farm Economic Association (AFEA) (Box 1, Folder 17)
- American Farm Economic Association Awards (Box 1, Folder 18)
- American Indian National Bank (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Archeology/Anthropology - Davis, Les (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Archeology/Anthropology - Lahren, Larry (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Arts and Humanities (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Assassination - John F. Kennedy (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Australia - New Zealand (Box 2, Folder 6)
- AVCO Corporation (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Babcock, Governor Tim (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Big Sky - Gallatin Canyon Study (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Big Sky Books (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Big Sky Books - Copyrights (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Big Sky Books - title(proposed): Bolton, Redant, Phillip D (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Big Sky Books - title: Community Development in Montana: resources, methods, case studies, Lassey, Wm. & Williams Anne S., Ed., 1970 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Big Sky Books - title: Failure on the Plains: a rancher's view of the public lands problem, Fulton, Dan, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Big Sky Books - title: Fishes of Montana, Brown, Dr. C.J.D., 1971 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Big Sky Books - title: From the St. Croix to the Potomac: reflections of a bureaucrat, Johnson, Sherman E., 1974 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Big Sky Books - title: Homesteading in Montana, 1911-1923: life in the Blue Mountain country, Bell, Edward J., 1975 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Big Sky Books - title: Montana as it Was, 1876: a centennial overview, Malone, Michael P. & Roeder, Richard E, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Big Sky Books - title: The Montana Frontier (reprint), Burlingame, Merrill G., 1980 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Big Sky Books - title: Montana in Maps, 1974, Taylor, Robert L., et al (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Big Sky Books - title: A Poet Goes to War, Martin, Earl E., 1970 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Big Sky Books - title: The Social Cost of Space in the Yonland, Kraenzel, Carl F., 1980 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Board of Regents (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Bonneville project - correspondence (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Bonneville project - manuscript (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Bonneville project - requests for materials (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Bookstore (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Campus unrest (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Campus unrest - Myers case (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Course changes in catalog (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Center for Advanced Studies (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Center for Industrial Development (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Center for Planning and Development (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Center for Political Economy and Natural Resources (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Cereal crop research (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Chambers of Commerce (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Coal development (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Coal Research Laboratory and Energy Fellowship Act, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Coal severance tax (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Coal slurry pipeline (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Colegio Cesar Chavez, lawsuit about accreditation, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Columbia Basin (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Columbia Basin - correspondence, 1960-1963 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Columbia Basin Consulting Board - financial papers (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Columbia Basin Consulting Board - reports, 1945-1960 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Columbia Basin Consulting Board - reports, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Columbia Basin Inter-Agency Committee (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Columbia Basin news clippings (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Columbia Basin Research Committee (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Commencement address, Highwood High School, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Commissioner of Higher Education (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Community Planning (proposed interdisciplinary Masters Degree) (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Community Planning - engineers (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Conservation education (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Conservation Education Committee (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Constitutional Convention (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Constitutional Convention Film (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Consultant assignments (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Cooperative Extension (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Cooperative State Research Service - research review (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Cost Study' correspondence (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Cost Study' manuscript: "Farm Organization and Production Requirements in Selected Irrigated Areas" (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Cost Study' materials (Box 5, Folder 5)
- D.A. Davidson letter (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Dakota Farmer correspondence and article manuscript (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Dean of Agriculture (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Dean of Agriculture congratulatory letters (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Dean of Science (Box 5, Folder 10)
- "Development and Population: Alternative Futures for the West" (conference), 1973 August 1-3 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- District Court (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Draft horses - assorted articles (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Dryland' correspondence (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Dryland' manuscript: "Production Costs on Selected Dryland Grain Farms" (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Dryland' materials (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Eck, Hugo G. - Coronary Column concept and the film "Tiger by the Tail" about it (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Economics and environment research and article clippings (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Education - miscellaneous clippings (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Educational television (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Endowment and Research Foundation (MSU) (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Endowment and Research Foundation (MSU): fund- raising (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Energy - miscellaneous clippings (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Energy policy - clippings (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Energy Research and Development Administration (ERDA) conference, 1975 November 3-4 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Energy Research Center (Box 6, Folder 10)
- England - Scotland (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Environmental conflicts - miscellaneous clippings, articles (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Environmental Protection Agency - proposal for investigation (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Environmental Quality Council (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Environmental seminars - MSU (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Environmental studies (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Environmental Task Force - based out of Bozeman and MSU (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Experiment Station research (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Faculty - general (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Faculty in Agriculture, primarily about Little International program (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Faculty Policy Advisory Committee, 1945-1957 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Family farms - miscellaneous articles (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Family farms and the community - articles and research notes (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Farm forums - programs (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Farm Policy Forum articles and correspondence (Box 7, Folder 14)
- Farm programs - miscellaneous clippings (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Farm Security Administration - Roy Huffman papers (Box 7, Folder 16)
- Farm Security Administration humor (Box 7, Folder 17)
- Federal Reserve Bank of Minnesota (Box 7, Folder 18)
- Federation of Rocky Mountain States, Inc. (Box 7, Folder 19)
- Feed - wheat study (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Fertilizer research (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Food and USDA - article (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Foreign trade - expansion program (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Forest Service (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Forestry Research Advisory Committee (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Franklin Delano Roosevelt articles (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Fulton, Dan A. - correspondence and assorted attachments (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Fulton gift books - appraisals and inventory (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Gallatin National Life Insurance Company (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Glacier Park meeting: Missouri and Columbia Basins Inter-Agency Committees (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Graduate Division - Montana State College, 1948-1953 (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Graduate Division - Graduate Council, agendas and courses (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Grand Canyon Symposium (Human condition relative to survival), 1970 June 14-18 (Box 8, Folder 14)
- "Great Decisions...., 1958", Foreign Policy Association promotion and publications (Box 8, Folder 15)
- Great Plains Agricultural Conference and associated papers, 1955 May 31 - June 2 (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Great Plains Agricultural Council, 1948-1965 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Great Plains Project, 1964-1965 (Box 9, Folder 2)
- Guam, University position (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Helburn, Nicholas - research proposal with assorted correspondence (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Highwood - Bobcat spring scrimmage (Box 9, Folder 5)
- Highwood Farm Loan Association (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Hokkaido University Seminar, 1982 October 21 (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Homesteading - newspaper clippings (Box 9, Folder 8)
- Honorary degrees - committee correspondence and vitae of candidates (Box 9, Folder 9)
- Hoover Commission (Box 9, Folder 10)
- Huffman, Roy E. - professional and personal correspondence files, A-B (Box 9, Folder 11)
- Huffman, Roy E. - professional and personal correspondence files, C-F (Box 9, Folder 12)
- Huffman, Roy E. - professional and personal correspondence files, G-H (Box 9, Folder 13)
- Huffman, Roy E. - professional and personal correspondence files, G-H (Box 9, Folder 14)
- Huffman, Roy E. - professional and personal correspondence files, L-O (Box 9, Folder 15)
- Huffman, Roy E. - professional and personal correspondence files, P-S (Box 10, Folder 1)
- Huffman, Roy E. - professional and personal correspondence files, T-Z (Box 10, Folder 2)
- Huffman Building (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Huffman Essay Award (Box 10, Folder 4)
- Huntley, Chet and the Big Sky project - articles (Box 10, Folder 5)
- Indian Bank study (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Indian policy (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Indians - Native American Studies Center (Box 10, Folder 8)
- Indirect benefits of irrigation correspondence (Box 10, Folder 9)
- Indirect benefits of irrigation materials (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Industrial development (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Institute of Applied Research (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Institutional economics (Box 10, Folder 13)
- Institutional seminar at MSU, 1966 August 2-5 (Box 10, Folder 14)
- Inter-cultural Studies - Mexico (Box 10, Folder 15)
- International Cooperation Center (Box 11, Folder 1)
- International Rural Development Conference, 1964 July 27-28 (Box 11, Folder 2)
- Investment in human resources (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Irrigation research (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Japan - assorted articles (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Jaycees (Box 11, Folder 6)
- Johnson, Leon H., President Montana State University (Box 11, Folder 7)
- Johnstone, William A -Stadium Campaign, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 8)
- Journal of Farm Economics (Box 11, Folder 9)
- Judge, Governor Thomas L (Box 11, Folder 10)
- Kellogg Foundation - Kellogg Extension Education Project (Box 11, Folder 11)
- Kellogg Foundation - proposal for Montana Center for Economic Development at MSU (Box 11, Folder 12)
- Kelso, Maurice M (Box 11, Folder 13)
- Kiwanis Club - Bozeman (Box 11, Folder 14)
- Kraenzel, Carl F (Box 11, Folder 15)
- Land Grant Colleges (Box 11, Folder 16)
- Land Grant Colleges - centennial publications and articles (Box 11, Folder 17)
- Land Grant University concept (Box 11, Folder 18)
- Land Grant University meetings (Box 11, Folder 19)
- Land use - articles (Box 11, Folder 20)
- Legal education - articles (Box 11, Folder 21)
- Legislative Council (Montana) (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Legislative Fiscal Analyst (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Legislature and the Montana Agricultural Experiment Station System, 1961 (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Letters to Editors (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Low-income farms - bibliography (Box 12, Folder 5)
- Lower Marias Development (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Lower Marias Irrigation Development Study - correspondence (Box 12, Folder 7)
- Lower Marias Irrigation Development Study - manuscript (Box 12, Folder 8)
- Lower Marias Irrigation Development Study - materials (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Mansfield, Senator Mike (Box 12, Folder 10)
- Maps (assorted - mostly Montana) (Box 12, Folder 11)
- Maryland, University of (Masters Degree and job offer) (Box 12, Folder 12)
- Master Plan - Division of Agriculture (Box 12, Folder 13)
- McIntosh, President Carl W., Montana State University (Box 12, Folder 14)
- Minor Civil Divisions of Montana, Map (Box 12, Folder 15)
- Missouri Basin Consulting (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
- Missouri Basin development and program (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Missouri Basin Interagency Committee meeting, 1968 July 27-28 (Box 13, Folder 4)
- Missouri Basin Research Committee (Box 13, Folder 5)
- Missouri Basin Survey Commission - correspondence (Box 13, Folder 6)